Daniel fantastic that was exactly the
third piece we needed and done so
gorgeously wonderful wonderful wonderful
wonderful so so let's jump into it and
maybe to two comments to kind of amplify
and you know dance with you here one is
I want to actually cite a text which is
a prophetic text if you'll meaning it's
anticipating from the 19th century that
appears in different forms in the great
traditions but I'll give you one of the
forms which appears in the tradition of
Hebrew mysticism and the text reads and
I'll read it in in Hebrew reads da Boa
so uh shockingly misawa so hooked which
means literally higher is the source of
the vessels than the source of the light
so we're used to understanding that
there's you know light that's held in a
vessel the vessel holds the light the
vessel is just a vessel but the light is
the light that's the real thing so for
example the body right is the temple of
the soul that's a classical expression
of but what's really important is the
soul and the body keep a healthy body so
you can hold your soul but in an
evolutionary unfolding we're now
realizing that split is actually a
limited split it's actually embodiment
begins to tell us that actually the body
itself holds spirit and the split
between body and spirit in which one is
a container for the other is actually a
false split and then you have this kind
of emergent property in the great
traditions which points towards this
notion that actually the vessels
themselves are even higher in their
source right then the light now I'm
gonna speak I'm gonna skip the kind of
the complex
you know Kabbalistic structures that
support that for a couple thousand years
but it's completely right for shouting
of course what you talked about so
beautifully and others technology right
it's not just the vessel right
technology is the light i technology is
an intrinsic part of the emergence and
the notion that technology is is merely
a vessel right that serves us actually
misunderstands right the nature of
reality itself in which it's actually
all a continuum right of emergence right
and in that emergent
which moved some inanimate to animate
and even the split between inanimate and
animate right is it kind of limited
split because of course
self-organization starts all the way
down and goes all the way up and so to
really highlight as he did so
beautifully that actually technology is
not an extra way that we need to
actually shift fundamentally how we
experience the word technology this
acknowledge is a natural expression of
the evolutionary process and therefore
will bring radical positive evolutionary
benefit it is enormous ly exciting yes a
moment we asked me just leave that will
come back second bite afterwards it's
kind of at that point on the table well
I completely agree with that mark and I
remember sometimes Bucky fuller was on
the stage
and somebody said to him dr. fuller I
don't like technology and he put out his
tummy so do you like your thumb what
happened there you had a thought there
was a tech name and you cut a nerve it
wouldn't do that is a key technique to
everything and he proclaimed that
technology will tend to be miniaturized
and ephemeral eyes as it is in our
bodies we don't even notice we have it
and so what you're saying seems now very
amazingly complex but think of our
bodies with the 50 trillion cells and
nature managed to do that and one of the
things I was thinking as you were saying
this that the same coordinating genius
of evolution that got all these
multicellular organisms up to a planet
that's just about to become a whole
system is at work here is both the
Technic technology the human intention
and the coordinating process of
universal creativity that inevitably
drives to higher order is working with
us in the most extraordinary way and as
you were speaking I was thinking if I
didn't believe that in the immense
coordinating genius of evolution I would
think this is too complex to do but then
I realize our bodies are too complex to
do grace
likes to do so I just want to ask the
question of both of you
what energetic organizational genius is
at work here along with this to to
empower it's because you can't think of
somebody's going to be President of the
US and do it right you can't think of
the United Nations doing it and you
can't think of any current power
structure doing it so marked here point
first about the vessels and the light
we've been reductionistic on both sides
right we've had spiritual traditions
that tried to reduce physics to an
epiphenomena of consciousness the
consciousness is what's fundamental it's
what's real all of this is my angry or
it arises from consciousness and then
we've had materialism that tries to
reduce subjectivity and consciousness to
the working of neural phenomena and
co-arising is a big insight and that the
whole distinction between the two as
separate is actually a mistake it's a
false dichotomy
they are the inside and outside of the
same thing this is a key to integral
theory it's a it's a key to getting any
complex system actually and so to have
an emerging physics spirituality that
recognizes the co-arising is so hugely
unique and beautiful and with society to
recognize the co-arising of the
evolutions in infrastructure in biology
and economics in our narratives that
they have to is really key thing and
then barber - what you're saying is so
so life does that right so we've got 50
trillion unique little creatures who are
coordinating together in a way it isn't
capitalist or communist or any system
we've had they don't sacrifice
themselves for others or others because
it's symbiotic so it's good for the
liver and the kidney is the same thing
when they're all interdependent and so
how does it do that and how can we do
that and so this is like you mentioned
before the
biomimicry or the Evo mimicry having our
built world reflect the intelligence and
complexity of the natural world because
we consciously start to understand it
more and apply it but then it's one more
step which is the part that excites me
the most is it in the anthill
you've got this amazing distributed
governance it's not a centralized
governance but it's also not a unique
self-governance because that all of the
ants as far as we understand so far are
interchangeable in their roles for each
other and so there's a different kind of
way that that's distributed but to have
a distributed governance that is
emergent where all the parts are unique
it's something that we've actually never
seen in that way and this is where
there's this beautiful concept of
evolution itself evolving that we're
looking at building upon and
transcending the principles of
governance that have happened so far
where what's needed for us is the next
step of evolution itself I'd like to
just comment because I experimented with
synergistic democracy as a title because
we did large conferences in big wheels
where we had all the different functions
health education economics and we asked
people three questions what do you want
to create what do you need to create it
that you don't have and what do you want
to share so everyone had the purpose of
realizing their unique self which was
their creativity but nobody could
realize it without the other sectors
participating and we actually did I
would say very crude demonstrations of
what a synergistic self-governance would
be and I'm just wondering if you see
that inherent in what you're saying that
there would be a way of that emerging
not really so for example you had a
technology right you had the wheel of
co-creation that created sectors and
then a process to have those sectors
interact with each other you had
questions I was technology right and the
fact that you didn't have higher
technology it was allowed to it was
capable of really identifying individual
needs and resources and matching them
was the limit of it we have the ability
to build those higher technologies so
part of the future of economics and
governance that I was foreshadowing is
we have the ability to have an inventory
of all the world's physical resources
real-time data input from sensors an
inventory of all of the needs
comprehensive metric systems of
everything we're seeking to optimize
roll into quality of life and complexity
processors that show as we are
I think one area how does that affect
all the other areas so there are no
externalities and what we do locally is
also what's best systemically which is
beyond the Dunbar capacity of one human
brain right now our computational
capacity now put all that together and
if we know all the resources we have to
work with we know everything we're
trying to optimize and this is all
flexible we can keep adding to it
we know how doing projects anywhere
affects everything else in light of all
of those metrics and we have forecasting
systems so we know timelines to affect
things we have the ability for a
fundamentally different kind of
governance and has ever existed before I
say that so let let's look to fantastic
it's been both be so that's bringing
back to Daniel and Barbara's piece
McKenna see where we are and she had
these three weeks kind of each kind of
merged together synergistically so one
you know in response to the second shock
of existence what do we need a
transformation of identity yeah I mean a
fundamental transformation of identity
and we need a fundamental reworking of
our essential understanding of how core
structures work that's the only way to
respond the second shock of existence we
can't respond you know patchwork so we
need an organismic response right which
highlights irreducible uniqueness and
yet understands uniqueness not as a
function of separateness it
disambiguates between separate and its
uniqueness right and allows for
uniqueness to emerge and separateness to
recede and and and that essentially is
the evolution of love yeah right because
actually the process that you were
describing Daniel right was actually a
process of evolutionary love outrageous
love driving the evolution of love and
you could in some sense say that
enlightenment means there are no
externalities yes the very definition of
enlightenment is there's no
externalities no one's outside the
system
no one's commodified no one is in
boobers terms Martin Buber the great
philosopher of dial up you know dialogic
s-- and it no one's in it everyone's
about and then what emerges that is and
here's the last piece is that you don't
lose your ability to excel that was the
Communist mistake right you don't
homogenized to borrow your phrase Daniel
beautiful phrase right actually you get
to excel you get to be unique self you
get to
Shyne as a matter of fact you must shine
not only you must shine it's the only
interesting thing to do right is to
actively actually be this kind of
shining expression that's unlike any
other and there will still be
hierarchies right meaning some people
will be better at this and other
probably better at that so we're not
it's not a leveling of differences it's
not a kind of bland oneness but it's not
a blodd enlightenment
once we actually employ the structure of
evolution evolving becoming conscious
more and more uniqueness and then
uniqueness as the currency of connection
and then you've got the evolution of
love happening through technology being
the natural expression of who we are
right then we've actually introduced a
possibility of a different world but we
have to be willing to let go of our core
structures of thought and reimagine
ourselves you know mark what this
reminds me of is the story of the
imaginal cells exactly within the body
of the caterpillar is they're programmed
identified internally with some type of
code is go build an antenna when the
time comes go build go build a wing and
self-assembly but by internal unique
self impulse if we right put it in the
imaginal sell worldwide experience with
emergence and unique self and essential
self and universal self is that everyone
has a unique gift to give and I don't
mean ordinary vocation right I really
mean unique outrageous love that when
you do it you're friendly in love right
that's different than ordinarily life
purpose or vocation and I just want to
bring up the point that I wonder if it's
true that each of us internally has that
frequency that when the system that
you're speaking of being just about
ready there's a some type of impulse or
call like we have when we're going to go
to war so everybody goes to war and they
build all these machines all of a sudden
I keep imagining maybe it's because I'd
love to make a call myself is it like
when I ran for vice-president I called
for be nominated
President of the United States to
suggest a piece from as sophisticated as
a Wharram map track and connect what's
working
I went trying to do that in 1984 and the
thing that was amazing is I got over 200
delegates and was nominated so I would
like to just offer the feeling that when
enough of us call for this and are able
to understand really what we're calling
for that it fills the the coat so called
vision gap that none of our political
leaders none of our social none of our
religious leaders are able to do it's
bottom-up self organizer and calling an
eloquence - yeah yeah no I mean just as
eloquent as John F Kennedy was yeah or
at our Gandhi or any of those great
people I think we need a kind of
greatness to make the call of the future
human for the future humanity and I just
would like to say I hope that this
course helps us assemble people willing
to call for this not only to be it but
to absolutely you know to stand for it
in in our culture all over the world
perfect I'm Bob reading your life work
really has been at the intersection of
technology and our story yes I think
technology motivated a question about
the inadequacy of our story for you yes
and for you saying a piece from as
sophisticated as the war room it's like
well what if we took the resource that
the Manhattan Project had to make the
bomb and solve world problems with it
that's the kind of thing you need to do
and to to the question about unique
differentiation symbiosis you talked
about the governance of the body so of
these 50 give or take trillion cells
they all have the DNA for the entire
body that's the place of what you called
yourself right they all have that
fractal integrity that holographic
integrity and then there's epigenetic
switches that make them totally unique
to do their particular role so they've
all got that true thing and then they've
got the unique thing and you don't want
a kidney trying to be a liver
a bone or a brain you need them all to
get this emergent property and you want
them working in great symbiosis and they
only ever compete for resources when
there's a fundamental scarcity and then
there's a prioritization of life support
and so the whole system works to try and
not have scarcity right and so when
there's not scarcity they work in huge
abundance and sharing and that's
identical to what we're doing in human
society it knows just about it
I want to know please just a very brief
dream I had the other night thinking
about the peace room as sophisticated as
a war room I had a vision of the
generals of the Second World War
Eisenhower Omar Bradley Tootsie Marshall
etc and it's not only because they
happen to it being Godfather's have my
half-brothers but they came to me and
said we're at your service folks right
the generals probably the last great
generals of epic that we've had in our
culture was at the Second World War they
did something that had to be done and I
would just like to call on the force
that's been in the military that's been
in the corporation's but particularly
the very brave generals and say yes it's
not just us it's it's all of us and they
have skills that we need yeah very very
beautiful yeah maybe just it's so
beautiful to close up and I think what
I'm about to say
Barbara you consider Daniel quítate and
said with your permission on a map of
all three of us what we've all implied
is that although emergence happens
through emergency right there's actually
an even deeper drive right that's
actually driving the emergence I talked
about unique self being the strange
attractor of the evolutionary process I
mean actually what we see is and this is
really critical everyone because this
shows that this is not a kind of crazy
utopia it's not a pipe dream it's
actually the central nature of reality
that it actually can on the fold this
way is actually the highest possible
creativity the highest possible vision
which actually pulls for itself right
it's the same thing that you began with
Barbara
right citing Brian that actually reality
decided not to stop at hydrogen and it's
actually not gonna stop at a broken
capitalism it's gonna move to a
conscious capitalism it's not gonna stop
at a broken Marxism which clearly failed
it's going to move to a higher
integration and actually that movement
has got to be driven by unique selves
and then the unique selves form this
unique self Symphony in which everyone
gets to transform and be gorgeous
and imagine if maybe to leave with this
vision what would be a great unique self
achievement you know you actually
created this stunning relationship with
your partner that was able to create an
entirely new form of art or you built a
new kind of a kindergarten I mean you
got wildly rewarded for that right and
you were admired for that and you got to
actually stand out for that because
we've actually changed right what our
value structures are that we're
rewarding and we have an externalized
creativity to basketball stars we pay
them to be creative so we can just be
you know ottoman talent without unique
selves we actually reincorporate art we
reincorporate transformation right as
right the core prime directive when we
reward it yeah
that changes the entire game yeah yeah
indeed if I could sum up everything that
I said in an essential way it would be
that we want to structurally change what
we condition and incentivize so that we
don't have to try and solve problems
that work still incentivizing but they
were obsoleting the problems by
incenting and conditioning more life
supporting fund a fundamentally more
life supporting functional behavior and
we can and when we see the problems that
trace to human behavior that trace to
how they were conditioned these are
changeable things and the evolution of
love requires not conditioning things
that limit the capacity for love like
stakeholder disalignment the system
right and that is really exciting yeah
so everyone this is the first three
sessions we've now laid out together
like the big picture the meta story the
meta vision in session one two and three
and now when we start the second
part of the course we're going to now
dive into how this applies right in life
in the most real and powerful ways